陛下
Your Majesty.
- 先生们 - 陛下
- Gentlemen. - Your Majesty.
此为何物
What's this?
教会评估调查 为本次调查之成果
The Valor Ecclesiasticus: the results of the Commissioner's.
调查专员对全国范围内所有修道院进行了核查
investigations into the wealth and practices.
核查内容涉及其财产及行为
of all the religious houses in Your Majesty's kingdom.
经查 大小修道院
It lists the treasures, the wealth and.
以及其它宗教组织
the vast private lands.
拥有大量私有土地
of the monasteries, priories and other religious establishments.
此外还有不计其数的放纵
It as well lists the innumerable cases of laxity,
堕落 邪恶 以及欺诈行径
corruption, evil practice.
恶行如此之猖獗 从未加以遏制
and fraud which have flourished, unchecked, and in some cases.
更有甚者 在同一宗教机构内竞持续了百余年
for hundreds of years, in these same institutions.
与此同时 陛下的国库亏空
Meanwhile, Majesty, your own treasury is much depleted.
本应臣服于陛下的臣民如此富有
Is it not a thing to marvel at,
而国库却入不敷出
the richness of those who ought by right to be your subjects,
这难道不令人讶异吗
and the poverty and debt of the English Crown?
所言极是
It is, indeed.
乔治
George!
亨利爵士
Sir Henry.
陛下 我为谢尔顿女士而来
Your Majesty. I came again to pay court to Lady Sheldon,
已获国王陛下恩准
with the King's permission.
- 是的 当然 - 我…
- Yes. Yes, of course.- I…
我借此向陛下表达我的爱戴及忠诚
I also wanted an opportunity to express my love and devotion to Your Majesty.
作为一名改革者
As a reformer myself,
我深谙您的功绩 虽不是为歌功颂德
I know all the good works you do, without ever seeking any praise,
但的确当之无愧
but always deserving it.
我到修道院视察时
When I visit religious houses,
力劝那些神职人员
I do so to urge those inside.
务必净化他们堕落的生活和教义
to cleanse and purify their corrupt lives and doctrine,
否则必定走向毁灭之路
or else they will surely be destroyed.
是的 的确如此
Yes. Yes, it's true.
我们福音派教徒必须脱胎换骨
We evangelicals must breathe new life into dead bones.
鼓励无知的人
and encourage the ignorant.
有所信仰
to believe in priority of faith.
信奉上帝箴言
and the word of God.
我们所见略同 亨利爵士
I see we understand each other, Sir Henry.
谢尔顿女士…
Lady Sheldon…
亨利·诺里斯爵士前来示好
Sir Henry Norris has come courting.
大人
My Lord.
臣告退
Madam.
- 您召见我？- 是的
- You wanted to see me? - Yes.
我又做了同样的梦
I had the dream again.
- 安妮 - 我早就说过
- Anne! - I told you!
- 我与她势不两立 - 看在上帝的份上
- I am her death and she is mine. - For God's sake!
只要她们还在世一天 我就不得安生
So long as they are both alive, I can't be safe!
凯瑟琳为什么还不死
Why doesn't Katherine just die?
所有人都跟我说她病入膏肓
Everyone keeps telling me how ill she is.
- 她为什么还不死 - 别说了
- Everyone keeps telling me how ill she is. Why doesn't she die? - Stop it!
我有一计 下次亨利出访外国
I had a thought. The next time Henry goes abroad,
我将摄政 我就可下令处死她们
I shall be left as Regent. I can just order their deaths.
你疯了 行了 别说了
You're crazy! Stop it! Stop it!
听我说
Listen to me.
你可是英格兰的王后
You're the Queen of England!
得有个王后的样子
For the love of God, act like it!
毕竟 你还侍奉过凯瑟琳王后
After all, you were a Lady to Queen Katherine.
她的一言一行 你都看在眼里
You saw and heard how she behaved.
依我之见 她从不会背叛自己的真实感情
It seemed to me she never betrayed her real feelings.
你就不能多向她学学？
Can you not be more like her?
向凯瑟琳学？
More like Katherine?
正是此意
Yes. You heard me!
至少表现出愉悦
At least seem happy.
而不是痛苦之态
Not a heap of misery!
院长神父 院长神父
Father Abbot! Father Abbot!
发生什么事了 约翰修士
What is it, brother John.
国王的信函
A letter from the King.
我们将被查禁
We are to be suppressed!
是克伦威尔阁下的命令
By the orders of Mr. Cromwell.
我不明白 给我看看
I don't understand. Give me the letter.
我们有何冒犯之处 神父
What have we done, Father?
不知道
I don't know.
会有什么灾难降临
What is to become of us?
您会再次召见法国大使吗
Will you ask the French Ambassador again.
如果弗兰西斯仍然不同意
if Francis will not relent and agree…
伊丽莎白与其子联姻
to the marriage of Elizabeth to his son?
- 我会的 - 您不认为此事很重要吗
- I might. - Don't you think it's important?
您难道不为我们女儿的未来考虑吗
And don't you think the future of your daughter is important?
- 我当然重视此事 - 那么 我…
- Of course, I do. - Well then, I.
你完全明白被弗兰西斯拒绝这桩婚事
Surely you understand that Francis' refusal.
是何等屈辱
to agree to the marriage in the first place was insulting!
你要我再回去乞求吗
Do you want me to go back and beg?
不 当然不是
No. Of course not.
亲爱的
Sweetheart…
已经确认过了
it's been tasted.
食物没有毒
It's not poisonous.
事实上
The fact of the matter is.
寻求与神圣罗马帝国结盟也许对我们更有利
it might be better for us to pursue an alliance with the Emperor.
- 这可合了凯瑟琳的意 - 这与凯瑟琳无关
- That would suit Katherine! - It has nothing to do with Katherine!
是为了英格兰
It has to do with England.
出于国家利益的考虑
And England's interests.
毕竟 这才是我本应关注的
After all, I am supposed to be concerned with that.
抱歉 宽恕我
I'm sorry. Forgive me.
不必道歉
You have no reason to be.
你关心的是我们的女儿 你当该如此
You care for our daughter, as you should.
但国家大事交由我来处理
But leave the greater things to my care.
听懂了吗
Do you understand?
能邀请大人伉俪前来
What a pleasure to have you.
我不胜荣幸
and your lovely wife to serve Your Grace!
跟我说说 你查禁了一些修道院？
So tell me, you're suppressing some religious houses?
是的 才刚刚开始
I am starting to, yes.
还有其它措施吗
Hm! And what else?
我打算废除开庭期间
I am intending to abolish.
和收获期间的
almost all the holy days that fall during the law terms.
几乎所有宗教节日
and during the harvest.
这些强制性的节日 严重影响了国家的经济
These forced holidays, they damage the country's economy,
阻碍了重要的行业 事实上他们使工人们穷困潦倒
stop vital works, and in fact, they also impoverish workers.
那些牧师你们打算怎么办？
And the priests?
至于那些神职人员 我们打算出台一系列法令
As far as the clergy are concerned, we mean to issue a set of injunctions.
要求他们大力鼓吹君权至尊
requiring them to preach the Supremacy.
还有一条法令是要求父母教导孩子
There will also be an injunction requiring parents and employers.
雇主教导仆人 学习用英语而不是拉丁语写的
to teach their children and servants the Lord's Prayer,
祈祷文 教义
Creed and the Ten Commandments in English.
以及十诫
rather than in Latin.
所有的神职人员都会被提示
And all clerics will be put on notice to attack.
去攻击围绕肖像和遗物的迷信祭拜活动
the superstitious cult surrounding images and relics.
他们会被告知 与其费精力财力在遗物上
They will be told it will more profit their souls to bestow.
不如救助贫困 更使他们的灵魂获益
upon the poor and the needy what they currently waste on relics.
这很好 先生们
That's very good, gentlemen.
但请允许我提个意见
But allow me to chide you.
我觉得你们做得还不够深入 不够迅速
I don't think that you're going far enough, or fast enough.
托马斯 令夫人是个激进分子阿
Your wife is, uh, quite radical, Thomas.
是啊 还是非法的
She is. And illegal.
因为这两个原因要把她藏起来
Two reasons to hide her.
你不能嘲笑我是躲箱子里偷运进来的
Being carried around in a box does not make you laugh.
亲爱的 对于这件事我很抱歉
My dear, I am sorry about that.
我不是你的「亲爱的」 我不是任何人的「亲爱的」
I am not your "dear." I am nobody's "dear!"
我是个女人 我要求我的想法能得到同等的尊重
I am a woman and I demand equal respect for my ideas!
对我而言 天主教的所作所为是邪恶的
For me, the practices of the Catholic church are evil!
他们把无知的民众蒙在鼓里
The way people are kept in total ignorance.
让他们为自己的身躯和思想感到罪恶
and made to feel guilty about their own bodies and their own thoughts.
甚至于 传播富人可以为他们的灵魂
And even worse, the idea that.
在天堂购置安息之地的想法
the rich can buy a plot in heaven for their souls!
我同意 天主教会已经堕落了 无可救药了
I agree with you.The Catholic Church is corrupted. It's irredeemable.
那你就应该毫不留情地
Then you should smash and destroy it.
彻底 完全地摧毁它
utterly and totally and without pity,
这就是我的建议 克伦威尔先生
that is my advice to you, Mr. Cromwell.
现在你可以把我放回箱子里了
Now you can put me back in my box!
晚安 主教大人
Good evening…Your Grace.
晚安 大臣阁下
Good evening, Mr. Secretary.
- 好了 - 驾
- Ready. - Hia! Giddyap!
你为什么在这里 托马斯
Why are you here, Thomas?
来看我们的落魄的样子？
To see the degradation that we have been forced to?
不是
No.
我不想看到这样 我不明白你为何要留下
I don't like to see it. I wonder why you stay.
为什么你不回到宫廷里？
Why don't you come back to court?
我爱戴王后
I love the Queen.
没有什么能让我离她而去
Nothing in this world will make me leave her.
我是天主教徒
I am a Catholic.
我相信我的信仰
I believe in my faith.
也许你们诗人什么都不相信？
Perhaps you poets don't believe in anything?
也许我们相信爱
In love, perhaps.
我允许你吻我
You may kiss me.
然后离开我吧
Then you will leave me alone.
永远别再来了
Forever.
伊丽莎白…
Elizabeth…
阁下？
Sir?
请原谅
Ah, forgive me.
我本应该提前通知您我即将来访的
I should have warned you of my impending visit.
请问你是谁？
Who are you?
我叫约翰·里兰 我是国王陛下的图书管理员
My name is John Leland.I am His Majesty's librarian.
我想你在修道院中有个图书馆是吗？
You keep a library in the priory, I believe?
确实如此 里兰先生
We do, indeed, Mr. Leland.
藏书中有很多杰出而古老的手稿和书本
It contains many fine and old manuscripts and texts.
我们为此而骄傲
We are very proud of it.
国王任命我仔细搜查所有隶属于
The King has commissioned me to peruse and diligently search.
将被查禁的宗教机构下的图书馆
all the libraries belonging to those religious houses about to be suppressed.
国王迫切地希望来保管
He is anxious to preserve.
所有他们的文学瑰宝
all their literary treasures.
- 你是说你要从这里取走这些资料？- 是的
- You mean you intend to remove them from here? - Naturally.
他们将被收藏于王室图书馆
They will be housed in the Royal Libraries.
但是…
But…
国王陛下还下令 让我查找
His Majesty has also ordered me to find texts.
强调王权至尊和认同新君主专制政体的文字
that would emphasize the Royal Supremacy and the New Monarchy.
里兰先生 我认为
I do not think, Mr. Leland,
你不会在这儿找到多少那样的文字
that you will find many such texts here!
王后陛下
Your Majesty?
伊丽莎白
Elizabeth!
我的心肝儿
Oh, my own heart!
妈… 妈妈
Ma… mama!
你好啊
Hello!
你可以下去了 布赖恩女士
You may leave us now, Lady Bryan.
我的小宝贝
My dear girl!
- 我的小甜心 - 你为什么走了？
- My sweetheart… - Why do you leave?
- 有没有想我？- 想
- Have you missed me? - Yes.
你想我了？我也想你呢
You missed me? I missed you!
日思夜想
So much!
这儿 还有这儿
Here! And here!
我看到一条
I see one!
我看到一条 我看到一条鱼了
I see one! I see a fishie!
你哪儿看到鱼了 小宝贝？
Where do you see a fishie, my darling?
- 你最近和王后谈过吗？- 是的
- Have you talked to the Queen recently?- Yes.
她让我开始担心了
She's giving me cause for concern.
任何人都看得出
Anyone can see that the King is not so much.
国王不再像从前那么爱她了
in love with her as he used to be.
她怎么了？
What's wrong with her?
我不清楚 也许她是在害怕
I don't know. Perhaps she's afraid.
可怜的乔治 你变得毫无主见了吗？
Poor George. Have you gone softheaded?
我？没有
Me? No!
希望如此
I hope not.
你知道的 乔治 风险太大了
You see, George, the stakes are too high.
今日做胆小的懦夫
Whoever is a coward now will soon rue the day,
他日必定悔不当初
and regret his misfortune.
成功之人只会在他人身上看到恐惧
Successful people only recognize fear in others.
去和你的妹妹再谈一次
Go and talk to your sister again!
- 好点没？- 好多了 谢谢
- Better? - Much, thank you.
女士们
Ladies.
这样是不是更好了 乔治
Is this not better, George?
好很多
Much better.
- 能请你跳舞吗 大人？- 现在不行
- Will you dance, My Lord? - No. Not now.
大人
My Lord.
每次都这样
All this time.
你还爱着她
and you're still in love with her!
你错了 大人
You're wrong, My Lord.
我的爱萌发和消逝在很久之前
My love was sprung and spent a long time ago.
国王陛下
Your Majesty.
马克
Mark!
拉一曲沃尔塔（旋转舞）
Play a volta.
我还想要怀孕
I want to conceive again.
我想怀个儿子
I want to conceive a son.
一个传承其父亲血脉的儿子
A son to be the living image of his father.
但我不能
But I can't.
为什么？
Why?
只要他们还活着 我就怀不了儿子
As long as they're alive, I can't conceive a son.
你说什么？
What are you saying?
凯瑟琳和她的女儿
Katherine and her daughter.
你是想要我处死她们？
Are you saying you want me to kill them?
玛丽…
Mary…
是你吗？
Is it you?
- 伊丽莎白 - 夫人
- Elizabeth. - Madam.
我已经有四年多没见到我的女儿了
I have not seen my daughter for more than four years.
把我们分隔开
Is it not cruel of them.
他们这样是不是很残忍？
to keep her from me?
尊贵的夫人 是的
Gentle Madam, yes.
这让我伤心欲裂
It burns my heart!
请再读一次元老院的判书给我听
Read the Curia's Judgment to me again. Please.
我们郑重宣告 亨利八世
"We pronounce that the marriage.
和阿拉贡的凯瑟琳之间的婚姻
"between Henry VIII and Katherine of Aragon.
确凿而且符合教规
"stands firm and canonical,
他们的子嗣
"and their issue.
依然合法正当
still stands lawful and legitimate."
看到了吧？
You see?
这是永恒的事实…
This is the eternal truth…
无人能否定的
which no man can ever deny.
圣父 诸位主教大人
Holy Father, Eminences,
我们即将商议的下一个议题是
The next item for our deliberation.
亚历山卓
Alessandro!
让我好好看看你
Let me look at you!
瞧 瞧 瞧
Well, well, well,
都长这么大了 快成一名男子汉了
how you've grown! You're almost a man.
- 做人要清正廉洁啊？- 是 爷爷
- Are you honest and clean? - Si, grandfather.
祈祷时 你有真正心怀谦卑吗？
When you pray to God, are you truly humble?
当然
Sure.
好孩子
Good boy.
去玩吧 假以时日定会是名杰出主教
Off you go. He'll make a fine Cardinal.
你们觉得呢？
Don't you think?
诸位大人 我们还有其他要事相商
Monsignors, we have other business to discuss.
其一 我邀请了名匠米开朗琪罗
First, I have invited the sculptor Michelangelo to paint.
为西斯廷教堂绘上《最后的审判》
a Last Judgment in the Sistine Chapel.
圣父 仍然有一部分大人
Holy Father, there are still people.
反对在天花板绘制他的作品
who object to his work on the ceiling.
我明白 我一度反对 但现在的确喜欢他的画
I know. I did myself. But now I like it.
这项工程会不会造价昂贵？
Won't the Judgment be expensive?
不会 我们无需支付太多的酬劳
No. We won't pay him very much.
毕竟 他不过是名画匠
He's only an artist, after all.
英格兰王的「要事」如何处理？
What of the King of England's Great Matter?
我来给诸位讲个故事吧
I will tell you a story.
年少时 有一次 我去游泳
Once, when I was a boy, I went swimming,
潮水把我冲走
and the tide carried me away,
远离海岸
far from the shore,
冲入深海
into the deepest water.
当时 我开始大声祈祷
It was then I prayed aloud to God,
然后一个波浪
and a friendly wave came.
又把冲回岸边
and pushed me back to the shore.
英格兰王也亦然
So it is with the King of England.
他被淫风恶浪冲离海岸
He has been carried far from the shore.
而他却毫不知情
but he does not know it.
他没有祈求上帝的帮助
He does not ask for God's help.
也没有请求我们的帮助
He does not ask for our help.
他自认为可以独自弄潮
He thinks he can swim alone.
但很快他就会意识到
But very soon he will realize.
他不是在游水而是在溺水
he is not swimming but drowning.
快 快…
Allez! Allez…
你哭哭啼啼地像个婴儿似的做什么？
Why are you crying like a baby?
这些不过是泥胎木像
These are nothing but idols!
快 快…
Allez! Allez…
神父 这伙人是谁？
Father, who are these men?
来自法兰西的布里多尼人
Bretons. From France.
- 胡格诺派教徒 - 新教徒？
- Huguenots. - Protestants?
对 大概克伦威尔大臣阁下觉得
Yes. Perhaps Mr. Secretary Cromwell felt that he couldn't.
他不能靠英国人来摧毁他们自己的传统
trust Englishmen to destroy their own heritage.
玷污他们自己的信仰
and besmirch their own faith.
王后驾到
The Queen!
- 陛下 - 陛下
- Your Majesty. - Your Majesty.
- 有何吩咐 陛下 - 我来见国王
- Excuse me. Your Majesty. - I came to see the King.
夫人 国王陛下今天早早就和沙福克公爵
Madam, His Majesty left early this morning.
出宫打猎了
to go hunting with the Duke of Suffolk…
… 还有其他贵族
and other nobles.
沙福克？
Suffolk?
是的 夫人
Yes, Madam.
想起来了 大王和我说过的
I remember now. He told me.
- 陛下 - 陛下
- Your Majesty. - Your Majesty.
干的漂亮 要启驾回宫了吗
A good kill. Do you want to get back to the palace?
不 附近有可以留宿的地方吗？
No. Is there somewhere around here we can stay?
有沃尔福宅邸
Uh, there's Wulfhall.
沃尔福宅邸 房子的主人是谁？
Wulfhall. Who owns that house?
约翰·西摩爵士一家
Sir John Seymour and his family.
我记得约翰爵士
I remember Sir John.
他在法兰西和我们并肩战斗过
He was in France with us.
我们去吧 给他个惊喜
Let's go surprise him.
驾
Hia!
约翰爵士 嘿
Sir John! Hey!
约翰爵士 约翰爵士
Sir John! Sir John!
来者何人？
Who is this shouting?
约翰爵士 你有位不速之客
Sir John, you have an unexpected guest.
- 陛下 - 约翰爵士
- Your Majesty! - Sir John.
不胜欢迎之至
You are most welcome!
主阿 你到我舍下
Domine, non sum dignus.
我不敢当
Ut intres sub tectum meum:
只要你说一句话
Sed tantum dic verbo,
我的仆人就必好了
Et sanabitur anima mea.
主耶稣基督
Corpus domini nostri jesu christi.
愿您的圣体保佑获得永生
Custodiat tu in vitam aeternam.
阿门
Amen.
厨子们办事拖沓 肯请陛下海涵
Your Majesty must forgive the tardiness of my kitchen.
朕深感约翰爵士招待热情 无微不至
I think I am very well looked after, Sir John.
朕刚刚还和公爵谈到法兰西之战
The Duke and I were reminiscing about the French campaign.
啊 是啊
Ah, yes!
只和他们对阵一次 实在是可惜啊
It was a shame we only fought one battle against them.
啊 但那是何等的战役啊
Ah, but what a battle!
微臣清楚记得 我军是如何对他们发起冲锋的
I remember how we charged at them, with His Grace.
公爵大人领军向前 勇敢无比
leading the vanguard with tremendous bravery.
法兰西阵脚大乱 兵败如山倒
And how the French were broken and routed in the charge and fled the field before us.
一眼望去 尽是被遗弃的马刺
All we saw were their spurs!
微臣需如实向陛下相告
I must tell Your Majesty that.
米兰大使对您可是仰慕不已啊
the Milanese Ambassador was amazed by you.
他对微臣说
He said to me,
「英王居然在战后比当初更加精神百倍
"The King was fresher after his exertion than before.
我不知道他何以至此「
I do not know how he can stand it!"
为过去的胜利干杯
To past victories.
为爵士干杯
To John.
玛丽吗？
Mary?
玛丽
Oh, Mary!
我的宝贝女儿…
My daughter…
我的小心肝
Oh, sweetheart!
是你吗
Is it you?
别哭 别哭 让妈妈好好看看你
Don't weep. Don't weep. Let me look at you.
乖 不哭了
There you are.
妈妈太久没有看到你了
I have not seen you for so long.
恍若隔世啊
An eternity.
终于见到你啦
And here you are!
哦 我的乖宝贝
Oh, my sweet child!
我的挚爱
My beloved child,
我的小天使
my angel,
我的世界
my world…
玛丽…
Mary…
我的珍爱
Mi preciosa.
她来过这了
She was here.
她来看我了
She came to me.
是的 夫人 我知道
Yes, Madam. I know.
我去召个御医吧
Let me summon a doctor for you.
不 不用了
No. I don't want a doctor.
我已经把自己
I have wholly committed myself.
全然托付给上帝的意愿
to the pleasure of God.
愿万能的主…
May the omnipotent God…
怜悯您
have mercy upon you.
宽恕您的罪过
and forgive you your sins,
愿耶稣基督带你走向永生
and may Jesus Christ lead you to eternal life.
马克 我伤心欲绝
Oh, Mark. I'm so sad.
所为何事？
Why sad?
要是我生的是男孩…
If I had a son…
要是我生的是男孩 我将带来辉煌盛世
if I had a son, it would bring about a golden world.
如此海泥 我倒是前所未见
I had never seen a sea of mud like that before!
我一时不知所措 我是说…
I didn't quite know what to think of it. I mean…
当时您的战马两只后腿都陷进去了
When your horse sank up to its hind quarters in it,
我永远都记得您的表情
I shall never forget your face!
- 我还能怎么办？- 我满身盔甲呢
- What was I supposed to do? - I was in full armor!
陛下 请允许我介绍我女儿 珍·西摩
Your Majesty, may I present my daughter, Lady Jane Seymour.
珍
Jane.
陛下
Your Majesty.
克伦威尔大人觐见
Mr. Secretary Cromwell is here.
夫人 您要召见我？
Madam. You wished to see me?
我父亲告诉我 您决定关闭英国境内
My father tells me you are determined to close.
所有的修道院 此事是否属实
every religious house in England. Is it true?
确有此事
Yes.
诚如陛下所知
As Your Majesty knows,
教会的调查专员发现欺诈 玩忽职守
the church commissioners found that fraud, laxity.
和滥用职权已经成了正常现象
and abuse were commonplace.
可有些教堂也获好评 对吗？
Yet some religious houses received good report. Is that not also true?
我还听说修道院的一切财富和资产
I also hear that all the wealth and assets of the monasteries.
都将转入国王名下
are to be transferred to the King's Treasury.
确实如此 我希望让国王成为
Indeed. I intend to make the King the most powerful.
整个欧洲最强大最富有的国王
and the richest King in Europe.
但是有些财富完全可以发挥更大的作用
But surely some of that wealth could be put to better uses!
- 更大的作用 夫人？- 是的
- Better uses, Madam? - Yes.
比如慈善捐赠和教育事业
For endowments to charitable and educational causes,
连渥西都知道这么做
which even Wolsey did!
夫人 听到您质疑国王钦定的的政策
Madam, I am surprised to hear.
我感到非常意外
you question the King's policy,
您的父兄对此也是全力支持的
which your father and brother whole-heartedly support.
我质疑的是政策本身 大臣阁下
I question the policy, Mr. Secretary,
因为我不相信这是国王制定的法令
because I am not convinced that it is the King's.
- 夫人 - 克伦威尔先生 您过于骄纵跋扈了
- Madam, I… - You are far too high-handed, Mr. Cromwell!
你要小心一点
You ought to be careful,
不然小心你的脑袋难保
or I will have you cropped at the neck.
愿全能慈悲的天主广施仁慈
Absolutionem et remissionem omnium peccatorum…
赦免我等罪过
vestrorum, misericors Dominus. Amen.
我知道我快死了
I know that I must die.
我恳请主清算我的罪孽
I ask that my debts be cleared.
并且我的仆人因她们
and my servants be recompensed.
对我精心的服侍
for the good service.
得到应得的报偿
they have done for me.
我期望被埋葬在信徒聚居的女修道院
I wish to be buried in the convent of the Observant Friars.
我期望我的灵魂会有500次弥撒来祷告
And I would wish that 500 masses be said for my soul…
会有人去
and that someone would visit.
位于沃尔辛海姆的圣母神殿
the Shrine of our Lady of Walsingham.
替我祷告
to pray on my behalf.
而我的女儿 玛丽…
To my daughter, Mary…
我将会把我从西班牙
I leave the collar of gold.
带来的黄金项圈
I brought from Spain…
和皮草留给她…
and my furs…
夫人 我来帮您
Madam, let me help you.
谢谢你 我忠诚的善良的伊丽莎白
Thank you, my loyal and loving Elizabeth.
我必须要给国王写信
I must write to the king.
「亲爱的夫君钧鉴…
"My Lord and dear husband…
「臣妾敬禀
"I commend me unto you.
值吾大限迫近久病沉痾之际
"The hour of my death draws fast on, and my case being such…
对你的绵绵爱意
"the tender love I owe you.
促使我牵挂你的安康和你灵魂的安宁
"forces me to put you in remembrance of the health and safeguard of your soul…
虽然思前想后你还是选择了肉体的需求
"which you ought to prefer above all considerations of the world of flesh whatsoever,
并为此将我置于痛苦的深渊
"for which you have cast me into many miseries,
由此你自身亦忧虑缠身
"and yourself into many cares.
对我而言
"For my part…
我全然宽恕你的一切
"I do pardon you all,
诚如斯言
"yea,
我期望并向我主祈祷
"and I do wish and pray dearly God.
恳求他也能宽恕你
"that He will pardon you also.
置诸其他事项
"For the rest,
专此奉禀
"I commend unto you.
对于我们的女儿 玛丽…
"our daughter, Mary…
如我一直渴望那样 伏祈你以慈父待她
"beseeching you to be a good father unto her as I have always desired.
最后
"And lastly…
我发誓
"I vow…
期盼见你一面乃我无上之愿
"that mine eyes desire you above all things."
伊丽莎白 帮我一下
Elizabeth, help me.
我们的帮助在于上主的圣名
Adjutorium Domini ets.
祂创造天与地 阿门
qui fecit caelum et terram, Amen.
父阿 我将我的灵魂交在你手里
In manus tuas commendo spiritum meum.
夫人
Madam!
南 什么事情
What is it, Nan?
现在我是真正的王后了
Now I am indeed Queen.
伊丽莎白
Elizabeth?
Elizabeth…
哦 上帝啊
Oh, Jesus!
伊丽莎白
Elizabeth…
- 噢 - 约翰 这是我太太 凯瑟琳
- Oh! - John. This is my wife, Catherine.
约翰爵士
Sir John.
王后陛下到了
Here comes Her Majesty now.
- 夫人 - 陛下
- My Lady. - Your Majesties.
两位陛下 亲爱的你去看会斗鸡吧
Your Majesties. Go watch the cockfight, sweetheart.
- 夫人 - 夫人
- My Lady. - My Lady.
马克 今天没表演吗？
Not performing today, Mark?
没有 今天没有 阁下
No, not today, My Lord.
不过今晚晚些时候可以？
But perhaps later tonight?
我不确定
I'm not sure.
你告诉她我的事了吗？
Have you told her about me? Hm?
- 我的事？- 没有
- About us? - No!
到底为什么不说？你可是乔治·波林
Why the hell not? You're George Boleyn!
在这你就像个铁血教父一样
You're like a bloody god around here!
斯米顿大师 如果你懂希腊语的话
If you could read Greek, Master Smeaton,
你就会知道连神都搞不定老婆
you'd know that even the gods had problems with their wives!
- 约翰爵士 - 陛下
- Sir John. - Your Majesty.
我们想向您的慷慨好客再次表示感谢
We wanted to thank you once more for your generous hospitality.
而且我们不请自来 尤其如此
All the more so because our visit was so unexpected.
陛下 这是我们最大的荣誉和快乐
Sire, it was the greatest possible privilege and pleasure.
陛下睡过的房间
And the room Your Majesty slept in.
将被永久命名为「国王的房间」
shall forever be known as "The King's bedroom."
您的女儿珍应该进宫
Your daughter Jane should come to court.
- 服侍王后陛下 - 万分感谢 陛下
- As lady to Her Majesty. - Thank you, Your Majesty.
您给了我们家族无比荣耀
You do our family a great honor.
宝贝 到这来
Sweetheart. Come here.
- 爸爸 - 哈
- Papa!- Ah!
我的伊丽莎白
My Elizabeth!
啊 警卫 警卫 保护我
Ah! Guards! Guards! Protect me!
快点来人
Now, men!
警卫 你们快点保护我 保护我
En garde! You're going to protect me. Protect me!
- 保护国王 - 妈妈
- Protect your King! - My mama!
伊丽莎白
Elizabeth!
爸爸
My papa!
我的伊丽莎白
My Elizabeth.
安妮
Anne.
什么事 父亲
Yes, father.
我听到些让人警觉的消息
I have heard some reports that alarm me.
什么消息
What reports?
好像你跟克伦威尔先生有点争执
It seems you have quarreled with Mr. Cromwell.
我们在
We disagreed.
一件非常重要的公众事宜上意见不和
on an important and public issue.
安妮 我把你捧上这个位子不是要你自作主张
Anne, I did not bring you up to have opinions.
或表达意见 或与国王亲近的人去争吵
or to express them or to quarrel with those closest to the Crown.
可我才是国王最亲近的 我是国王的妻子
But I am closest to the Crown! I am the King's wife!
你要记清楚你是怎么走到这一步来的
And you should remember how you got there!
我知道我怎么走到这的
I know how I got there.
不是全靠你
And it was not all you.
It was not all you.
也不是诺福克或者乔治
or Norfolk or George.
更不是任何其他你要说的人
or any other man you want to name!
也有我的功劳
It was also me.
他爱上的人是我 他尊重的是我…
He fell in love with me. He respected me…
和我的见解
and my opinions.
你笑什么？
What is it?
你用不着担心
You have no need to worry.
到处都是好消息
There is good news all round.
凯瑟琳已经死了…
Katherine is dead…
而我…
and I…
已经怀孕了
I am pregnant.
你明白吗？
Do you understand?
我怀着
I am carrying.
国王的儿子
the King's son.
我们面前是个金色的世界
We are on the edge of a golden world!